Guide to the Michael Ivanovitch Rostovtzeff Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Photographs, [ca. 1914-1938, undated]; Series II; 4 linear feet (10 boxes)
  - Section A
    - Samartia - antiquities, undated (Box 22, Folder 71)
      See also: box 26, folder 137
    - Scythia - antiquities, undated (Box 22, Folder 72)
      See also: box 26, folder 149
    - Social & Economic History of the Hellenistic World
      - Athens, undated (Box 22, Folder 73)
      - Louvre, undated (Box 22, Folder 74)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 22, Folder 75)
    - Sumeria - art, undated (Box 22, Folder 76)
    - Sumeria - objects, undated (Box 22, Folder 77)
    - Syria, undated (Box 22, Folder 78)
    - Syria - objects, undated (Box 22, Folder 79)
    - Tibet, undated (Box 22, Folder 80)
    - Varia Asiatica, undated (Box 22, Folder 81)
    - Vexillum and Victory, undated (Box 22, Folder 82)
  - Section B
    - African antiquities, undated (Box 23, Folder 83)
      See also: box 18, folder 1
    - Agripinilla stone, undated (Box 23, Folder 84)
    - Alexandrapol - tumulus, undated (Box 23, Folder 85)
    - Al-mina, 1938 (Box 23, Folder 86)
    - Bulgaria - antiquities, undated (Box 23, Folder 87)
    - Chertomlyk-Varonegh(?), undated (Box 23, Folder 88)
    - China - art, undated (Box 23, Folder 89-93)
      See also: box 18, folder 3-8
    - China - objects, undated (Box 23, Folder 94-95)
      See also: box 18, folder 9
    - China and Samartia - drawings, undated (Box 23, Folder 96)
    - Elizavatiaskaya-Stanitza, undated (Box 23, Folder 97)
    - Goths, undated (Box 23, Folder 98)
    - Holmes, C. R. - collection, undated (Box 23, Folder 99)
    - India - miscellaneous, undated (Box 23, Folder 100)
    - Italy - Mystic, undated (Box 23, Folder 101)
    - Karanis Fayam (?), undated (Box 23, Folder 102)
    - "Kleinasiatische and Syrische Goffer …", 1933 (Box 23, Folder 103)
    - Lepetildra - exacavation, objects, 1914-1915 (Box 23, Folder 104)
    - Loo, C. T. - collection, undated (Box 23, Folder 105)
    - Loo, C. T. - collection, undated (Box 24, Folder 106)
    - Luristan bronzes, undated (Box 24, Folder 107-116)
    - Merovingian - antiquities, undated (Box 25, Folder 117)
    - Merovingian art, undated (Box 25, Folder 118)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 25, Folder 119)
    - Miscellaneous - bronzes, undated (Box 25, Folder 120)
    - Near East Museums - objects, undated (Box 25, Folder 121)
    - Norway - ancient woodcarving, undated (Box 25, Folder 122)
    - Nympheus and Chersunis - Jewels, undated (Box 25, Folder 123)
    - Persia - art, undated (Box 25, Folder 124)
      See also: box 21, folder 60-61
    - Persia - objects, undated (Box 25, Folder 125)
    - Pompeii, undated (Box 25, Folder 126)
    - Rumanian - objects, undated (Box 25, Folder 127)
    - Russia (Box 25)
      See also: box 22, folder 70
      - East Russia and Siberia - art, undated undated (Box 25, Folder 128)
      - Kiev, notes, undated undated (Box 25, Folder 129)
      - South Russia and China, undated undated (Box 25, Folder 130)
      - South Russia and Pergamon, undated undated (Box 25, Folder 131)
      - South Russia - art, undated undated (Box 25, Folder 132)
      - South Russia - art and objects, undated undated (Box 25, Folder 133)
      - South Russia - jewels, undated undated (Box 25, Folder 134)
      - South Russia - miscellaneous, undated undated (Box 26, Folder 135)
      - South Russia - objects, undated undated (Box 26, Folder 136)
    - Samartia - antiquities, undated (Box 26, Folder 137)
      See also: box 22, folder 71
    - Samartia - art, undated (Box 26, Folder 138-139)
    - Samartia - jewels, undated (Box 26, Folder 140)
    - Samartia - objects, undated (Box 26, Folder 141-143)
    - Samartia - Roman art, undated (Box 26, Folder 144)
    - Scandinavia - Teutonic art, undated (Box 26, Folder 145)
    - Scythia - antiquities, undated (Box 26, Folder 146-148)
      See also: box 22, folder 72
    - Scythia - antiquities/Bulgaria-antiquities, undated (Box 26, Folder 149)
    - Scythia - art, undated (Box 27, Folder 150-151)
    - Scythia - objects, undated (Box 27, Folder 152)
    - Scythia - Persian bronzes, undated (Box 27, Folder 153)
    - Semibratnij Kurgan - tumulus, undated (Box 27, Folder 154)
    - Siberia art, undated (Box 27, Folder 155)
    - Slavic antiquities, undated (Box 27, Folder 156)
    - Solobha - Tumulus, undated (Box 27, Folder 157)
    - Syria - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 27, Folder 158)
    - Teutonic Style - art, undated (Box 27, Folder 159)
    - Theangela, undated (Box 27, Folder 160)
    - Thracian Mithras, undated (Box 27, Folder 161)
    - Torluhics - arts (?), undated (Box 27, Folder 162)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 27, Folder 163)
    - Uruk Bullae (?), undated (Box 27, Folder 164)
- Lectures, 1920-1944; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series contains a group of addresses, arranged chronologically, which includes Rostovtzeff's lectures at the University of Wisconsin (1920-1924), Yale University and other institutions (1925-1944), and a group of public lectures (1944, n.d.).
  - University of Wisconsin, 1920-1924 (Box 28, Folder 165-168)
  - Yale University and other institutions
    - "Classical civilization", 1926-1926 (Box 28, Folder 169)
    - "Les classes rurales …", 1926 (Box 28, Folder 170)
    - "L'Art de L'Asie Centrale…", 1927 (Box 28, Folder 170)
    - "History of the Orient and Greece, Problems of Chronology", 1926-1927 (Box 28, Folder 171)
    - Hellenistic Italy, 1926-1927 (Box 28, Folder 172)
    - History of the Orient and Greece, 1926-1927 (Box 28, Folder 172)
    - Twelve lectures--Dura Europos, South Russia, China, India, and Miscellaneous, 1928-1941 (Box 28, Folder 173)
    - "Persia, India, China", 1929 (Box 29, Folder 174)
    - "Bronze schallen aus Sud", 1931 (Box 29, Folder 174)
    - "Some aspects of Iranian Art", 1933 (Box 29, Folder 174)
    - Animal style - eight lectures at Norwegian Academy of Science, Oslo, Norway, 1928 (Box 29, Folder 175)
    - "L'empereur Tibere et le culte imperial", 1930 (Box 29, Folder 176)
    - "Notes d'Archeologie Orientale…" "Le porte-epee des Iranian", 1931 (Box 29, Folder 177)
    - "Alexander the Great and the Hellenistic Period," I-XXX, 1931, undated (Box 29, Folder 178)
    - "The Hellenistic Age," I-XXII (incomplete), 1931, undated (Box 29, Folder 178)
    - "Some Remarks on the Luristan Bronzes", 1931 (Box 29, Folder 179)
    - Caravan cities, 1932 (Box 29, Folder 180)
    - "The Great Hero of Middle Asia and his exploits", 1932 (Box 29, Folder 181)
    - "Alexander the Great", 1934-1935; 1937-1938 (Box 29, Folder 182)
    - Roman Syria, 1935 (Box 29, Folder 183)
    - "Horace as I see him", 1936 (Box 29, Folder 184)
    - "L'importance de Dura-Europos, son histoire", 1937 June (Box 30, Folder 185)
    - "Dura - Europos on the Euphrates" (drafts), 1938 (Box 30, Folder 186)
    - "Some remarks on the monetary and commercial policy of the Seleucids and Attalids", 1939 (Box 30, Folder 187)
    - Archaeology and history, 1940-1941 (Box 30, Folder 188)
    - "Ancient Hisotry and Archaeology", 1941-1942 (Box 30, Folder 189)
    - "The Greek City-State", 1943-1944 (Box 30, Folder 190)
    - "Entwichlung der Decorative Mahlerei", undated (Box 30, Folder 191)
    - "Development of the Decorative Painting", undated (Box 30, Folder 191)
    - "Some Features of the Economic and Social Life of Egypt in the Third Century B. C.", undated (Box 30, Folder 192)
    - Undergraduate lectures, undated (Box 30, Folder 193)
    - Graduate lectures (Box 30, Folder 194-195B)
  - Public lectures
    - "The Ancient and the Modern Worlds", 1944 (Box 31, Folder 196)
    - "Business prosperity and Cultural prosperity", undated (Box 31, Folder 197)
    - Pompeii, Italy, Africa, antiquities, undated (Box 31, Folder 197)
    - 1-17, undated (Box 31, Folder 198)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 31, Folder 199)
- Writings and Miscellanea, Series IV; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series contains writings and miscellanea by Rostovtzeff and others. Material is arranged alphabetically by type and title in General and Select sections.
  - General
    - Articles, 1943; 1949; undated (Box 32, Folder 200-201)
    - Bibliographies - notes, undated (Box 32, Folder 202-203)
    - Book reviews, undated (Box 32, Folder 204-207)
  - Select
    - Alexander the Great, undated (Box 32, Folder 208)
    - Amazones, undated (Box 32, Folder 209)
    - "The Bosporan Kingdom", undated (Box 32, Folder 210)
    - Dura Europos, 1928-1939; 1952; undated (Box 32, Folder 211-213)
    - Encyclopedia Italiana, undated (Box 33, Folder 214)
    - Fettich, Nandor - writings, 1934; undated (Box 33, Folder 215)
    - Greek - English manuscripts, undated (Box 33, Folder 216)
    - Greek - French manuscripts, 1940; undated (Box 33, Folder 217)
    - Greek - German manuscripts, undated (Box 33, Folder 218)
    - Iran
      - Iranian Art, 1933 (Box 33, Folder 219)
      - Iranian Hero, 1929-1932; undated (Box 33, Folder 220)
    - "Lex Mansiana and other African Inscriptions", undated (Box 33, Folder 220)
    - Monumentum Ancyranum - Sir William Ramsay, 1914; 1924-1925; undated (Box 33, Folder 222)
    - Near East
      - About the Near East - manuscripts, undated (Box 33, Folder 223)
      - "The Near East under the Roman Empire"; "Hellenism in the Near East", 1941; undated (Box 33, Folder 224)
    - Palmyra
      - "Les inscriptions…", 1932 (Box 34, Folder 225)
      - "The Caravan Gods…" (Box 34, Folder 226)
      - "The Squatting Gods…", 1932; 1937 (Box 34, Folder 226)
    - Prefaces and additions— A History of the Ancient World, undated (Box 34, Folder 227)
      See also: Series I
    - Writings—Zahn, Robert, 1940; undated (Box 34, Folder 228)
    - Writings—others, 1939; undated (Box 34, Folder 229)
    - Miscellaneous writings and notes, 1937; undated (Box 34, Folder 230-232)
- Additional Material, 1918-1981; Accession 2005-M-007
  - Correspondence
    - General Correspondence, includes loose photographs, 1926-1943, [1981], undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Letters from relatives in Russia, [1920]-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-10)
  - Financial
    - Business correspondence with P. M. Kousmichoff and Sons, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bank statements, 1918-1925 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Identification documents
    - Michael Rostovtzeff, 1918-1929 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Sophie Rostovtzeff, 1918-1929 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lectures
    - "Ancient and Modern Worlds" [unpublished], undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Dura Europos" [unpublished], undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Dura Europos Synagogue", 1933, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Scandinavian lecture tour, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Writings
    - Articles in Russian [probably from newspapers]
      - "India and Its Art", post 1937 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - "Italy Does It Herself", post 1932 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - "To the Memory of Paul N. Miliukoff", [1942] (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Das Bosporische Reich" [manuscript in German]
      - Chapter 4: 1, 2, 3 ch 4: 4, 5, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Chapter 4: 4, 5, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Articles [original order retained]
      - "Greco-Iranian Art", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "Note on the Gens Julia and Gens Augusta at Corinth", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - L'Académie des Inscriptions et Belles Lettres et Son Oeuvre en Syrie, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "Les Matres Gauloises et la Terra Mater Greco-Romaine", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "L'Art Imperiale Romana", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "Der Mittelasiatische Tierstil in S. Russland und China", undated
      - "The Foundation of Dura Europos on the Euphrates", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - "Parthian Art and the Motive of the Flying Gallop", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - "Hadad and Athargatis of Palmyra", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - "Il Rebus Sator", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - "Augustus As Reflected in the Monuments of Art of His Period", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Romana Africa", manuscripts, typescripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Roman Empire, notes for the second edition, undated (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - Social and Economic History of the Roman Empire, notes for a new edition, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Zur Politischen Entwickelung Sythiens" ch 3: 1, 2, 3 [manuscript in German], undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Reviews of books by Michael Rostovtzeff, 1924-1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 31-34)
    - Press clippings and notices
      - Social and Economic History of the Roman Empire, 1926-1929 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - History of the Ancient World, Vol. I, 1926-1928 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - History of the Ancient World, Vol. II, 1927, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - The Animal Style and Mystic Italy, 1928, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Out of the Past of Greece and Rome and Caravan Cities, 1932, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Unidentified, 1939, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)